[English subtitles are available]
[본 영상은 한글자막을 제공합니다]
[Road Home]
[귀로 : 너에게 돌아가는 길]
[Episode 2]
[제2화]
It's snowing. Drive slowly.
눈 오니까 천천히 운전해
Okay.
알았어
What are you looking for?
뭐 찾아?
This.
이거?
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
Thank you so much. See you next time.
정말 고마워요, 나중에 또 봐요
Thank you.
고마워
No worries.
아니야
Bye.
잘 가
Don't you want to get up?
안 일어날 거야?
I pretended so hard.
제가 힘들게 연기하는 걸 봐서라도
Can't you
얘기 좀
talk to her more?
더 하지 그러셨어요
How pointless it would be
할 얘기가 없는데
if I fumbled for something to say.
뭘 더 해
In my view, you have a lot to say.
할 얘기가 많아 보이던데요?
In your view?
네가 그걸 어떻게 알아?
How old are you?
너 몇 살인데?
What can you tell?
네가 뭘 알겠어?
Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모를
You like her, don't you?
좋아하는 거 맞죠?
Silence
대답 안 하시면
means a yes.
인정하는 거예요
When we were eating just now,
아까 밥 먹을 때
I asked them about their schedule.
제가 스케줄 물어봤어요
They will depart from town in two days
며칠 뒤에 마을에서
to the city.
시내로 떠나신대요
And they're not traveling for work.
일은 없고
They came for sightseeing.
관광만 할 거래요
Are you playing dumb?
모르는 체할 거예요?
This is not your personality.
옌천 삼촌답지 않은데요?
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
I'm not playing dumb.
모르는 체하는 게 아니라
I'm just lazy to answer.
대답하기 귀찮은 거야
Do you think
네가 스케줄 물어본 걸
I didn't hear your question?
내가 몰랐을 것 같아?
Did you eavesdrop on our conversation?
몰래 엿들었던 거네요
Sit back.
똑바로 앉아
You can't talk to the driver in a car.
운전할 때 운전자랑 얘기하면
Don't you know that?
안 되는 거 몰라?
♫How did I get hooked on you?♫
♫ 어쩌다 그대를 사랑하게 됐을까 ♫
♫I'm asking myself♫
♫ 스스로에게 물어봤지 ♫
♫I can give up anything♫
♫ 모든 걸 포기할 수 있었던 나였건만 ♫
♫But I'm reluctant to leave today♫
♫ 오늘은 왠지 떠나기 싫어 ♫
♫You're not beautiful♫
♫ 넌 그렇게 아름답지는 않지만 ♫
♫But you're exceedingly adorable♫
♫ 아주 사랑스러워 ♫
♫Oh, Cinderella♫
♫ 오 신데렐라여 ♫
♫My Cinderella♫
♫ 나의 신데렐라여 ♫
♫I'm constantly breaking your heart♫
♫ 난 항상 네게 상처를 줬지 ♫
♫I'm always being cruel♫
♫ 난 항상 모질었지 ♫
♫I told you not to take it seriously♫
♫ 마음에 담아두지 마 ♫
♫'Cause I can't believe it♫
♫ 그건 내 진심이 아니니까 ♫
You're so persistent.
참 대단해
You keep on exercising
매일 운동을 하네
every day.
계속할 거야?
Wait for me to finish.
곧 끝나
You have such a good figure.
몸매 관리하는 거 혹시
Women dress up for their beholders.
좋아하는 남자 때문이야?
Women dress up to satisfy themselves.
난 날 위해 하는 거야
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Were you in a relationship with Captain Lu before?
너 과거에 루 대장님과 사귀었었지?
To be honest,
솔직히
when I saw you two
너희 두 사람이
sitting side by side in the car,
차에 나란히 앉아있었을 때
I felt something was off.
분위기가 심상치 않았어
Nope.
아니야
We are alumni.
그냥 동창이었어
It seemed awkward
할 얘기가 없으니까
because we shared no topic.
어색해서 그런 거야
Your former classmate is too courteous.
네 동창은 너무 체면을 차린다
I wanted to buy him some supplements,
보양식 좀 선물하려 했더니
but he refused.
싫다고 하네
Lu Yanchen?
루옌천 말이야?
Yes.
응
He helped us twice.
우리를 두 번이나 도와줬고
Last night,
게다가 어제저녁에는
he even saved our lives.
목숨까지 구해줬잖아
So I suggested buying some supplements
그래서 내가
for him.
보양식을 좀 선물하려 했지
I also offered to buy food and supplies
남자애한테는
for the little boy.
먹을 거랑 쓸 거 좀 주려고 했는데
But he refused everything.
다 사양했어
No way.
안 돼
My husband said
우리 남편이
I must show my gratitude.
감사 인사는 꼭 해야 한다고 했어
[People's Police Training Base]
[인민 경찰 훈련기지]
[SWAT Detachment]
[경찰특공대 사단]
Your transfer application
자네의 전근 신청이
has been approved.
받아들여졌네
I was kidding.
방금 그거 농담이었어
Lu Yanchen.
루옌천
Yes.
네
In February next year,
다음 해 2월
you will be officially transferred to Tianwen City
자네는 톈원시에 가서
to be the captain
톈원시 공안국
of the Third Brigade
경찰특공대 사단
in the SWAT Detachment of Tianwen City Public Security Bureau.
제3대대 대대장으로 임명될 걸세
Tianwen City is very close to Beijing.
톈원시는 베이징과 가까우니까
Now,
그때 되면
you can often
가족과
reunite with your family.
자주 만날 수 있겠네
Whose idea is this?
어느 분께서 그렇게 하신 겁니까?
It's mine.
내가 한 거야
What's wrong?
왜?
Do you have a problem with your former leader?
상사한테 불만이라도 있나?
I haven't decided yet.
전 아직 결정을 못 내렸습니다
No need for you to decide.
그러든 말든
It's a deal.
이미 결정은 내려졌네
I know
자네가 힘들어하는 걸
you have something on your mind.
나도 알아
But you shouldn't stop here.
하지만 자네는 더 크게 성장해야 해
I won't reason about
비전 같은 얘기를
a bright future with you.
하려는 게 아니야
I just want to tell you
자네는
you are my pride after all these years.
내 자랑이고
It's not easy to cultivate you.
자네를 어렵게 키웠다는 것만은 알았으면 좋겠네
You, Lu Yanchen,
루옌천 자네는
are born to do this.
타고난 경찰이야
For the country,
나라를 위해
you must devote yourself entirely.
자네는 반드시 모든 걸 바쳐야 해
Yes.
알겠습니다
After arriving there,
톈원시에 가서
do your best.
열심히 해
I failed.
바라던 대로 안 됐네
My resignation wasn't allowed. Instead of that, I was promoted.
사직은 못 하고 오히려 승진을 했어
You knew it?
알고 있었어?
How is that possible?
그럴 리가
I guessed it.
그냥 내 추측이야
What kind of person are you? Explosive Ordnance Disposal Hero.
넌 폭발물 처리팀의 영웅이잖아
If I were the leader,
내가 상사였어도
I wouldn't let you go home and do nothing.
널 절대 전역시키지 않았을 거야
I'm leaving.
가자
Meet you at the same place on the weekend.
주말에 자주 가던 가게에서
We'll give you a farewell party in advance.
송별회를 해야지
Is it Aunt Gui Xiao?
구이샤오 이모 생각하세요?
Even the scenes in TV dramas
드라마에서도
don't have a character like you.
삼촌처럼은 안 해요
It can't be mentioned or spoken of.
얘기도 못 하게 하다니요?
It's not.
그런 거 아니야
So what?
아니면 됐어요
That only means
삼촌은
you have something on your mind.
고민이 있는 게 분명해요
If there's nothing,
두 사람 사이에 아무것도 없다면
since she came all the way here
구이샤오 이모가 모처럼 왔는데
you should entertain her.
같이 놀거나 식사하는 정도는 해야죠
Give me your homework.
숙제한 거 가져와 봐
I haven't finished yet.
아, 아직 다 못했는데요
Give it to me.
가져오라고 했어
If there's one mistake,
한 문제라도 틀리면
you aren't allowed to go out tomorrow.
내일 외출 금지야
You're a tyrant.
폭군이네
Do you want to move back to your place?
여기 있기 싫어?
No.
아니에요
I just want to be with Uncle Lu.
옌천 삼촌이랑 같이 있고 싶어요
When will my dad come?
아빠는 언제 와요?
Soon.
곧 올 거야
Why are you just sitting here?
그냥 앉아있지 말고
Have some peanuts and sunflower seeds.
땅콩이랑 해바라기씨 좀 먹어요
My treat.
내가 쏘는 거예요
Captain Lu, congratulations on your promotion.
루 대장님, 승진한 거 축하해요
It's a normal work transfer.
그냥 인사이동일 뿐이에요
You're so modest.
겸손하시네요
Go on.
계속해
Sister-in-law.
형수님
-Sister-in-law. -You're here.
- 형수님 - 다들 왔어
Hurry and give me some help.
얼른 도와줘요
I can't handle it alone.
나 혼자 못하겠어요
Sure.
네, 알겠습니다
Okay.
알겠어요
Sister-in-law, where is Captain Lu?
형수님, 루 대장님은요?
Let’s go.
들어가자
He went to buy you drinks.
술 사러 갔어요
It's snowing these days.
눈보라 때문에
The drinks delivery guy didn't come.
술을 배달해주는 사람이 못 왔어요
The drinks are not enough for you.
술이 적어서 어떡해요?
The captain's wallet is about to cry.
루 대장님이 크게 한턱내야겠는데요
Thank you.
일 보세요, 형수님
It's prettier than this.
이것보다 예뻐요
Not bad.
대단하네
Xiaonan, you're good at drawing.
샤오난, 그림 잘 그리는구나
It's a work of art.
잘 그렸네
Amazing.
대단해
Of course.
그럼요
Give me a hand.
와서 도와주지 않고 뭐 해?
Why are you laughing?
뭘 웃어?
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
We saw your ex-girlfriend.
대장님의 전 여친을 봤어요
At first, we didn't believe
샤오난이 말할 때까진
what Xiaonan told us.
안 믿었는데
Captain Lu, your subconscious action
루 대장님이 무심코 돌아보시는 걸 보니까
has betrayed you.
진짜였네요
Get things done!
얼른 와서 도와
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
Is your ex-girlfriend married?
전 여친분 결혼하셨나요?
I'm just caring about her.
궁금해서 묻는 거예요
Even if you broke up,
헤어져도
you could still be friends, right?
친구는 될 수 있잖아요
Yes.
맞아요
I even went to
전 제 첫사랑의
my first love's wedding
결혼식에 가서
with the biggest red packet.
축의금을 두둑하게 냈다고요
Don't tell us
전 여친분께서 설마
she came to Qining
치닝에
for her honeymoon.
신혼여행을 오신 건 아니겠죠?
That's sad.
좀 슬퍼지네요
The one who can subdue Captain Lu
루 대장님의 마음을 가져간 사람이
married someone else.
다른 사람과 결혼했다니
What a pity.
아주 아쉽습니다
Are you done?
얘기 다 했어?
Captain Lu. Please arrange for us to meet her.
루 대장님, 전 여친분 좀 만나게 해주세요
We rarely gather together.
모처럼 만났는데요
We broke up long ago.
오래전에 헤어졌는데
How are you supposed to meet her?
무슨 핑계로 또 만나?
Captain Lu, you don't understand.
루 대장님, 그건 아니랍니다
First love is always the best.
첫사랑은 제일 아름다운 거예요
At least,
다른 여자들과는
it's different from others.
다르다니까요
Anyway, we suggest you
아무튼 전 여친분이 오셨으니
take the privilege as a host to entertain her,
밥 한 번 사드리는 게 좋겠어요
right?
안 그래요?
Yeah, you are the host.
맞아요, 밥은 사드려야죠
Yes, Captain Lu.
맞아요, 루 대장님
We need to show them
전 여친분께
our enthusiasm.
저희의 열정을 보여드려요
[Ma's Fine-quality Beef and Mutton]
[마지 정육점]
The whole one.
어제 갓 들여온
Do you want the sheep...
양고기예요
-Does this... -we just bought yesterday?
- 그거 선물하면 - 사실래요?
show my sincerity?
받는 분께서 좋아하실까요?
Of course.
그럼요
I want two.
2마리 주세요
Unfortunately, only one is left.
아쉽게도 1마리밖에 안 남았어요
I give it to you
목숨을 구해준 은인에게
because you want to thank your savior.
선물한다고 하셔서 남겨둔 겁니다
Okay, thank you.
네, 감사합니다, 사장님
No problem.
네
Finally, he replied.
드디어 답장이 왔군
I thought
나한테 가짜 전화번호를
it was a fake number.
준 줄 알았잖아
There was no reply from that day.
여태껏 답장이 없었단 말이야
I texted him three days ago,
사흘 전에 문자 보냈는데
but he just replied today.
오늘에서야 답장이 왔어
Who is it?
누구?
Captain Qin.
친 대장님
I asked for his phone number
그날 식사할 때
during dinner that day.
전화번호를 달라고 했거든
Boss, hurry up.
사장님, 서둘러주세요
Today,
오늘
they are all having a farewell dinner
이 근처에서
nearby.
송별회를 한다고 했어
Let's go over there.
같이 가보자
Why should we go
그 사람들끼리 식사하는데
to their gathering?
우리가 왜 가?
Do you think I'm so inconsiderate?
내가 아무것도 모를 줄 알아?
Captain Lu asked you to go.
루 대장님이 널 만나고 싶다면서
He wants to meet you.
널 데려오라고 하셨어
I'm doing this
난 루 대장님의
to repay Captain Lu's kindness.
은혜에 보답하려고
I have to complete the task.
그러는 거야
I can give him the gift in passing.
가는 김에 선물도 하고 말이야
He asked me to go?
루옌천이 날 만나고 싶다고 했다고?
Impossible.
그럴 리 없어
Look.
이것 봐
Captain Lu wants to meet Miss Gui Xiao.
루 대장님이 구이샤오 씨를 만나고 싶어 하니까
Please invite her over.
데려오세요
I'll treat her to a meal.
제가 한턱 낼게요
I'm not going, really.
난 진짜 안 갈래
Hello.
여보세요
Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모
My dad and Uncle Lu are drunk.
우리 아빠랑 옌천 삼촌이 취하셨어요
Please come over quickly.
빨리 오세요
Everyone has left.
다른 분들이 다 가셔서
I can't handle them myself.
저 혼자 어떡해야 할지 모르겠어요
There are so many people.
동료들이랑 같이 술 마셨는데
They can't really
설마
leave them alone.
정말 두 사람만 남겨두고 갔겠어?
When I was your age,
이모는 네 나이 때
I stopped telling such lies.
그렇게 쉽게 들통날 거짓말을 안 했단다
Is she coming?
온대?
Try what I just taught you.
내가 가르쳐준 대로 해봐
Aunt Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 이모
Are you Uncle Lu's first love?
옌천 삼촌의 첫사랑 맞으시죠?
Uncle Lu is drunk.
옌천 삼촌이 취하셨어요
Poor him.
되게 불쌍해요
His eyes are red.
눈시울이 다 붉어져서
And he is talking about your past
우리 아빠랑
with my dad.
이모와의 과거를 얘기하는 중이에요
You...
너...
Keep an eye on them.
네가 잘 지켜드려
It's late, so I won't go over there.
이모는 늦어서 못 가
It's not dark yet.
아직 대낮이잖아
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오...
Ask him for an address.
주소 달라고 해
You're such a little smart cookie.
너 참 대단하구나
How did you persuade him?
어떻게 설득한 거야?
It's just teamwork.
다들 같이 생각해낸 거예요
Aunt Cai,
야야 이모
I'll leave the rest to you.
남은 건 이모한테 맡길게요
Leave it to me?
나한테 맡긴다고?
I'd love to
목숨을 구해준 은인이랑 엮어줄 수 있어서
do matchmaking for my savior.
영광이야
Send me the address. Hurry.
얼른 주소 보내
Boss, hurry up.
사장님, 서둘러주세요, 저희 급해요
Okay.
알았어요
Here, scan here will do.
자, QR코드 여기 있습니다
It's paid.
결제됐죠?
Okay.
네
♫How much I want to go back home♫
♫ 고향에 돌아가고 싶어 ♫
♫To be by her side again♫
♫ 그녀의 곁으로 돌아가고 싶어 ♫
♫To see her kindness and gentleness♫
♫ 착한 그녀가 ♫
♫To soothe my broken heart♫
♫ 내 마음의 상처를 보듬어줄 거거든 ♫
♫Let me go back home♫
♫ 고향에 돌아가고 싶어 ♫
Hello.
안녕하세요
We're looking for Captain Lu.
루 대장님 찾으세요?
Come in.
얼른 들어오세요, 어서요
♫To soothe my broken heart♫
♫ 내 마음의 상처를 보듬어줄 거거든 ♫
Come in, please.
자, 안으로 들어가세요
♫The year you set off into the twilight♫
♫ 그해 넌 타향으로 떠났고 ♫
♫You thought there was something there♫
♫ 그곳에 네가 바라는 것들이 있는 줄 알았지 ♫
Stop singing.
그만 불러
Captain Lu is inside.
루 대장님 안에 계세요
Just go inside.
들어가시면 됩니다
I'm here
루천을
just to see him.
보러 온 거잖아
Give them some space.
두 사람이 얘기 나누도록 해요
Yes.
네
♫Can you hear me?♫
♫ 들리나요 ♫
♫All these years♫
♫ 오랜 세월 ♫
♫The anticipation from the depths of my soul♫
♫ 내 영혼 깊은 곳에서 온 기대 ♫
♫An ethereal heart♫
♫ 공허한 마음 ♫
♫A healed wound♫
♫다 나은 상처 ♫
♫The eagerness to wait for you has overtaken the anxiety♫
♫ 당신의 마음을 기다리며 불안함을 떨쳐요 ♫
♫Turning around and brushing past♫
♫ 돌아서 당신을 지나쳐요 ♫
♫I'm the only one left in the world♫
♫ 세상에 홀로 남은 기분이에요 ♫
♫Waiting for fate to take its course♫
♫ 운명이 정해지길 기다려요 ♫
♫Listen to the sound of approaching footsteps♫
♫ 가까워지는 발걸음 소리를 들어요 ♫
♫In a flash, I'm not paying attention♫
♫ 그 순간 ♫
Lu Chen.
루천
♫The whole heart has fallen and lost its soul♫
♫ 넋을 잃어요 ♫
♫I accept the push of destiny♫
♫ 정해진 인연을 받아들여요 ♫
♫And embrace the extraordinary love♫
♫ 평범하지 않은 사랑을 끌어안아요 ♫
♫Can you hear me?♫
♫ 들리나요 ♫
Why are you here again?
왜 온 거야?
♫All these years♫
♫ 오랜 세월 ♫
♫The anticipation from the depths of my soul♫
♫ 내 영혼 깊은 곳에서 온 기대 ♫
What do you want?
대체 뭘 어쩌려는 거야?
♫An ethereal heart♫
♫ 공허한 마음 ♫
I wouldn't have come if you hadn't called me.
네가 부르지 않았으면 나도 안 왔을 거야
♫A healed wound♫
♫다 나은 상처 ♫
I called you?
내가 널 불렀다고?
♫The eagerness to wait for you has overtaken the anxiety♫
♫ 당신의 마음을 기다리며 불안함을 떨쳐요 ♫
Gao Hai.
가오하이!
What's wrong, Captain Lu?
왜 그러세요? 루 대장님
Come.
이리 와
Come closer to me.
더 가까이 와
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
Apologize.
사과해
Well...
그게...
I'm sorry, Miss Gui Xiao.
죄송해요, 구이샤오 씨
Just now,
아까는
I pretended to be Captain Lu.
제가 루 대장님 목소리를 흉내 낸 거였어요
I always like to
제가 평소에
imitate people's voices.
성대모사를 즐겨 하거든요
I'm just kidding.
제가 장난을 쳤습니다
For the sake of mission,
가오하이가 임무 수행 때문에
he has been
성대모사를
learning voice imitation for years.
몇 년 배웠었어요
It does sound similar.
비슷하게 흉내 내긴 하는데
How could you make such a joke?
그래도 그렇지 어떻게 그런 장난을 쳐?
Gui Xiao, I'm sorry.
구이샤오 씨, 미안해요
It's okay.
괜찮아요
You imitate it
흉내를
quite well.
잘 내시네요
Miss Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 씨
On behalf of my second hometown,
저희의 두 번째 고향인
Qining,
치닝과
on behalf of our brigade, I welcome you.
우리 대대는 구이샤오 씨를 환영해요
You will definitely fall in love with Qining.
치닝이 마음에 드실 겁니다
Just like you do with your hometown.
고향처럼 느껴지실 거예요
This is Captain Lu's favorite place.
여기는 루 대장이 가장 좋아하는 곳이에요
By the way,
참
the mutton here is delicious.
여기 양고기가 아주 맛있어요
Captain Lu is unoccupied now.
루 대장은 이제 한가하니까
Captain Lu, remember to
루 대장, 꼭 구이샤오 씨랑 같이
take them there to eat.
양고기 먹으러 가
You guys continue.
두 분 얘기 나누세요
I'll leave you alone.
전 이만 갈게요
They are used to fooling around,
동료들이 평소
without having a sense of propriety.
장난을 많이 쳐
Sit.
앉아
Shouldn't you apologize first?
사과부터 해야지 않아?
Captain Lu.
루 대장
Please excuse me.
미안
I was rude just now.
방금은 내가 지나쳤어
I just heard on the phone that
아까 전화에서
no one could handle you when you were drunk,
네가 취해서
and you were talking nonsense
술주정 부리면서
about our past.
우리 과거 얘기를 한다고 했어
Then I heard you call my name.
네가 내 이름을 부르는 소리도 들었는데
So I came because I was afraid something would happen.
실수할까 봐 온 거야
Since it's a misunderstanding,
오해인 걸 알았으니까
I'm leaving now.
갈게
Have a seat.
잠시 앉아
I'll send you back later.
이따가 집에 데려다줄게
I've been here for days.
여기 온 지도 며칠 됐으니까
You don't have to see me off.
나 혼자 돌아갈 수 있어
Anyway,
어차피
there will be no next time.
앞으로 다시 만날 일은 없겠네
Lu Chen, if you dare to hang up on me,
루천, 내 전화를 그냥 끊어버렸다가는
You'll never see me again.
다신 나랑 볼 생각하지 마
So soon?
벌써 나왔어?
It hasn't been 10 minutes yet since I entered the house.
들어간 지 10분도 안 됐는데
My head hurts.
머리 아파
I don't feel well.
몸이 안 좋아
Let me see you off.
바래다줄게요
I've known her for years.
제가 오랜 친구라서 잘 아는데
She is really angry now.
구이샤오가 정말 화난 것 같네요
Don't worry.
걱정하지 마세요
I'll talk to her later.
제가 설득해볼게요
Thank you.
고마워요
Do you want to drive?
네가 운전할 거야?
See you, Captain Qin.
나중에 또 봬요, 친 대장님
Bye.
조심히 가요
Let's go.
가자
I'm not defending Captain Lu.
루 대장님 편을 드는 거 아니니까 잘 들어
You may not know something.
네가 모르는 일이 있어
Qin Mingyu told me
방금 친밍위 씨가 그러던데
their former captain had perished in the line of duty
지난주에
last week.
이전의 대장님께서 돌아가셨대
He said the captain had guided
그 대장님은
and supported Captain Lu all the way.
루 대장님을 키워주셨던 분인데
But, he died right in front of Captain Lu.
안타깝게도 루 대장님 앞에서 돌아가셨대
Captain Lu resigned because he blamed himself.
루 대장님은 죄책감 때문에 사직하신 거래
Lu, try to comfort her.
옌천, 핑계를 찾아서 설득 좀 해봐
Uncle Lu.
옌천 삼촌
Aren't you cold?
춥지도 않나?
Anything else, Captain Lu?
또 무슨 일이야? 루 대장
Do me a favor.
도움이 필요해
Cai.
야야 씨
Captain Lu.
루 대장님
Please go ahead.
말씀하세요
I really need your help.
정말 도움이 필요합니다
I want that kid
방금 그 아이를
to study in Beijing.
베이징에 있는 학교에 보내려고 하는데
Can you
좋은 학교를
find me a prestigious school?
좀 알아봐 주실 수 있습니까?
You want to go to Beijing
아까 그 아이랑
with that kid?
베이징에 가시려고요?
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
If it's simply a transfer to another school,
일반적인 전학이니까
you don't need to ask for help.
굳이 부탁할 필요 없어
You've been in Beijing longer than me.
넌 베이징에서 오래 살아서
You're more familiar than me.
나보다 잘 알잖아
Do me a favor.
좀 도와줘
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
Think of it as helping me.
날 도와주는 셈 치고 도와드려
This is on my account.
내가 너한테 빚진 거라고 쳐
I'm not a kid anymore
어릴 때처럼
to lose my temper.
심술부리지 말자
He apologized.
사과까지 했는데
There's no point in unforgiving.
계속 이러면 안 돼
I'll go back to Beijing the day after tomorrow.
난 모레에 베이징으로 돌아가
But this is not
하지만 이 일은
as simple as you think.
생각보다 복잡하니까
We need to work out the details.
자세히 얘기해 봐야 해
Take the kid to Beijing
아이를
as soon as possible.
얼른 베이징에 데려와
It'd be better to get it done during the winter vacation.
겨울방학이 끝나기 전에 데려오는 게 좋을 거야
Don't delay his class.
수업 듣는 데 늦으면 안 되니까
Let's discuss this now.
지금 얘기하자
Now?
지금?
Do it now.
지금 얘기해요
You've helped me
이렇게 큰 도움을
a lot.
주셨으니까
As his father,
아빠인 제가
I should show my gratitude.
한턱 내야죠
Come in and have a bite.
들어와서 같이 식사하세요
We won't let Captain Lu drink tonight.
오늘 저녁에 루 대장더러 술 마시지 말고
Let him drive you home.
이따가 바래다 드리라고 할게요
That's right.
그러자
I haven't eaten anything yet.
나 아직 아무것도 못 먹었어
Captain Qin, is there any food inside?
친 대장님, 안에 먹을 거 있어요?
Anything you want.
다 있으니까
Help yourself. It's on my treat.
마음껏 주문하세요, 제가 사겠습니다
No need.
아니에요
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
I really didn't know
네가 불려 온 걸
you were called here.
정말 몰랐어
Forget it.
됐어
You know
내가 사과에 약한 걸
I buy the apologies.
너도 알잖아
I'll be fine if you say sorry.
네가 미안하다고 하면 난 금방 괜찮아져
I'm sorry.
미안해
♫It was a hurry♫
♫ 급히 떠나는 길 ♫
♫I saw you off with a song♫
♫ 노래로 배웅해 ♫
♫We were drunk in the wind♫
♫ 긴 바람 따라 ♫
Have a seat.
앉아
♫And parted in different directions♫
♫ 우린 흩어져 ♫
Alright, stop singing.
그만 불러
Just listen to the song quietly.
노래나 들어
♫No need to say anything♫
♫ 말하지도 말고 ♫
You guys talk first.
그럼 두 분 얘기하세요
♫No need to understand♫
♫ 알 것도 없어 ♫
It's about your son.
친 대장님 아들 일인데
What should we talk about without you?
저희 둘이 무슨 얘기를 해요?
♫A million miles across in a dream♫
♫ 꿈 속에서 천만리를 건너 ♫
I'm going to look for food.
먹을 것 좀 찾아볼게
♫A year simply passed by♫
♫ 봄 여름 또 가을 겨울 ♫
♫As long as you glanced back♫
♫ 고개를 돌려 본 걸로 ♫
Tell me the details.
자세한 상황을 얘기해 주세요
♫That would be enough♫
♫ 충분해 ♫
Let me make this clear.
먼저 얘기해둘 게 있어요
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오 씨
♫When the flowers fall♫
♫ 꽃잎이 떨어질 때 ♫
Even if you fail,
내게 도움을 주지 못하더라도
I'm still grateful to you.
감사하게 생각합니다
♫We'll meet again♫
♫ 우린 또 만날 거니까 ♫
Don't mention it.
인사치레는 안 하셔도 돼요
Say something important.
본론부터 얘기해 주세요
♫It was a hurry♫
♫ 급히 떠나는 길 ♫
Here's the thing.
그게 말이죠
I'm divorced
제가 이혼하고
♫I saw you off with a song♫
♫ 노래로 배웅해 ♫
and I took Xiaonan with me.
샤오난을 홀로 키우고 있어요
I'm usually
제가
busy with the team
평소에 부대 일이 바빠서
♫We were drunk in the wind♫
♫ 긴 바람 따라 ♫
while Xiaonan is studying at a school on a temporary basis.
샤오난을 돌봐줄 사람이 없기도 하고
No one takes care of him.
혼자 학교를 다녀야 해서
Poor thing.
아주 안쓰러워요
♫And parted in different directions♫
♫ 우린 흩어져 ♫
My household registration was in Beijing.
제 호적은 원래 베이징이었는데
♫The fog is thick♫
♫ 자욱한 안개 ♫
I was transferred here because of work.
일 때문에 치닝으로 옮겨왔어요
When Xiaonan was born,
샤오난은 태어날 때
♫I should never forget my original intention♫
♫ 맨 처음을 잊지 않아 ♫
his household registration was under his mother.
엄마의 호적을 따랐고요
♫I used a bird to deliver the letter♫
♫ 구름 속 편지 ♫
That's the situation.
이런 상황이에요
I can transfer back
난 나랑 샤오난의 호적을
♫And hoped for a reply♫
♫ 먼 곳에 있는 그대를 그리워 해 ♫
our household registration.
옮겨갈 수 있어
But I want him
그런데 일단 샤오난을
to study in Beijing for a few years
베이징에서 학교를 다니게 하고
♫The years are rippling♫
♫ 세월이 흐르고 ♫
and live on campus
중학교에 입학할 무렵에
when he's in junior high school.
기숙사에 보낼 생각이야
♫On both sides of the crowd♫
♫ 멀리 떨어져 있는 그대와 나 ♫
♫Old wishes are hard to come true♫
♫ 되돌릴 수 없는 추억 ♫
He's too young.
샤오난은 너무 어려요
I, as an outsider,
부모가 아닌 저도
♫Old dreams are vanquishable♫
♫ 지나간 꿈은 연기처럼 ♫
don't feel at ease listening,
걱정스러운데
let alone you, his birth father.
아빠이신 친 대장님은 오죽하시겠어요
♫And there's nothing left but sighs♫
♫ 한숨만 남기고 ♫
♫The sound of memories never goes away♫
♫ 추억은 멀지 않은 곳에 ♫
I helped Yaya's relatives
작년에 야야의 친척을 도와
♫It should be the fallen leaves and frost♫
♫ 낙엽이 지고 서리가 내려 ♫
with the same issue last year.
전학 절차를 밟아본 적이 있어요
♫I wish seeing the handwriting in your letter is like seeing you in person♫
♫ 편지에 그리움을 담아 ♫
It's very similar.
지금과 비슷한 상황이었어요
The transfer only requires a regular procedure.
전학은 일반적인 수속이라
♫The past has not been left unattended♫
♫ 지나간 추억은 계속 그 자리에 ♫
It doesn't matter who handles it.
누가 하든 다 똑같아요
But it can be a hassle
하지만 지금
♫With ink as a sail♫
♫ 먹이란 돛을 달고 ♫
to transfer his household registration
호적을 옮기고 수속하려면
♫Tossing and turning between my fingers♫
♫ 손가락 사이를 오가네 ♫
and go through the process.
좀 번거롭고
It may take a long time.
시간도 오래 걸릴 거예요
♫The distance between us is far away♫
♫ 먼 곳에 있는 그대 ♫
So I suggest you
제 생각에는
find a private school
일단 사립 학교에
♫Even if we don't meet each other♫
♫ 만나볼 수는 없어도 ♫
for a one-semester transition.
한 학기쯤 다니다가
♫My longing can overwhelm a thousand mountains♫
♫ 그리움은 멀리멀리 ♫
After the household registration is done, then transfer him to a public school.
호적을 옮긴 다음에 공립 학교로 가는 게 좋겠어요
♫It's like it was yesterday♫
♫ 마치 어제처럼 ♫
Got it.
알았어
You can't go back yet, right?
지금 당장은 돌아갈 수 없는 거지?
♫Where can we see the full moon?♫
♫ 보름달이 뜬 그곳 ♫
How are you going to find a school for him?
학교는 어떻게 찾을 거야?
I'll take care of it.
내가 할게
How about this?
이렇게 해요
I'll recommend the school to you.
제가 학교를 추천해드릴게요
I have friends
제 친구 자녀가
whose children are in school.
학교를 다녀서
They are familiar with the school.
학교에 대해 잘 알아요
I'll go through the transfer procedures
전학 수속도
♫It was a hurry♫
♫ 급히 떠나는 길 ♫
for you too.
제가 도와드릴게요
After all, I've done it before
제가 해봐서
and I'm familiar with the process.
절차를 잘 알거든요
♫I saw you off with a song♫
♫ 노래로 배웅해 ♫
Thank you so much.
정말 감사합니다
♫Look at each other without words♫
♫ 말없이 마주보는 ♫
♫This heart is the same♫
♫ 그 마음은 같아 ♫
When are you going back to Beijing?
언제 베이징에 돌아갈 거야?
♫The fog is thick♫
♫ 자욱한 안개 ♫
I haven't finished
이쪽 일이
my work here.
아직 안 끝났어
♫Don't ask about my feelings♫
♫ 그 속에 숨은 진심 ♫
♫I'll tell you all my sorrows♫
♫ 이별의 슬픔을 고하네 ♫
You guys continue.
둘이 얘기해
You and our sister-in-law...
너랑 형수님...
♫In the bright moon♫
♫ 밝은 달빛을 향해 ♫
♫The years are rippling♫
♫ 세월이 흐르고 ♫
Talk with our ex-sister-in-law.
전 형수님과 얘기 나눠
♫On both sides of the crowd♫
♫ 멀리 떨어져 있는 그대와 나 ♫
♫Old wishes are hard to come true♫
♫ 되돌릴 수 없는 추억 ♫
♫Old dreams are vanquishable♫
♫ 지나간 꿈은 연기처럼 ♫
♫And there's nothing left but sighs♫
♫ 한숨만 남기고 ♫
♫The sound of memories never goes away♫
♫ 추억은 멀지 않은 곳에 ♫
♫It should be the fallen leaves and frost♫
♫ 낙엽이 지고 서리가 내려 ♫
♫I wish seeing the handwriting in your letter is like seeing you in person♫
♫ 편지에 그리움을 담아 ♫
♫The past has not been left unattended♫
♫ 지나간 추억은 계속 그 자리에 ♫
♫With ink as a sail♫
♫ 먹이란 돛을 달고 ♫
Have some beef jerky.
소고기 육포 좀 먹어
♫Tossing and turning between my fingers♫
♫ 손가락 사이를 오가네 ♫
I'll get you some water.
물 가져올게
Lu Chen.
루천
♫The distance between us is far away♫
♫ 먼 곳에 있는 그대 ♫
I'm not thirsty.
됐어, 목 안 말라
♫Even if we don't meet each other♫
♫ 만나볼 수는 없어도 ♫
♫My longing can overwhelm a thousand mountains♫
♫ 그리움은 멀리멀리 ♫
♫It's like it was yesterday♫
♫ 마치 어제처럼 ♫
♫Where can we see the full moon?♫
♫ 보름달이 뜬 그곳 ♫
The atmosphere is good.
무드를 살려줄 거예요
Do you two
두 사람 혹시
want me to go back and persuade her?
저보고 구이샤오를 설득하라는 거예요?
Are they really first love?
두 사람 정말 첫사랑이래요?
Kind of.
그럴 거예요
Did Captain Lu tell you?
루 대장님이 그러셨어요?
My son figured it out.
샤오난의 추측이에요
When he first came to Qining,
샤오난이 치닝에 막 왔을 때
he lived with Lu Yanchen.
루옌천네 집에 살았었는데
There's a sketch
서랍에서
in Captain Lu's drawer.
스케치 한 장 발견했었어요
It's Gui Xiao.
그게 구이샤오였어요?
He didn't even tell me.
옌천은 저한테도 얘기 안 하다가
A few days ago, he spilled it out.
며칠 전에 무심결에 말하더라고요
But Captain Lu's
근데 루 대장의
sketching skills
그림 실력이
are definitely the top.
아주 뛰어나서
It's almost the same as the photo.
사진과 거의 비슷해요
Many brothers are drunk.
애들이 많이 마셔서
I have to watch over them.
내가 돌봐줘야 해
No need to see me off.
바래다주지 않아도 돼
♫I can give up anything♫
♫ 모든 걸 포기할 수 있었던 나였건만 ♫
♫But I'm reluctant to leave today♫
♫ 오늘은 왠지 떠나기 싫어 ♫
Captain Lu. Captain Lu.
루 대장님, 루 대장님
♫You're not beautiful♫
♫ 넌 그렇게 아름답지는 않지만 ♫
♫But you're exceedingly adorable♫
♫ 아주 사랑스러워 ♫
♫Oh, Cinderella♫
♫ 오 신데렐라여 ♫
♫My Cinderella♫
♫ 나의 신데렐라여 ♫
♫I'm constantly breaking your heart♫
♫ 난 항상 네게 상처를 줬지 ♫
♫I'm always being cruel♫
♫ 난 항상 모질었지 ♫
You didn't drink.
넌 술 마시지 않았잖아
Aren't you going to see them off?
구이샤오 씨를 바래다주지 그랬어
♫I told you not to take it seriously♫
♫ 마음에 담아두지 마 ♫
These people are here.
여기 아직 애들이 있잖아
Is the story between you and your ex-girlfriend
전 형수님과
♫'Cause I can't believe it♫
♫ 그건 내 진심이 아니니까 ♫
really unforgettable?
꽤 애틋한 사이였나봐?
I've never seen you like this.
네 이런 모습 처음 봐
♫You're so beautiful♫
♫ 넌 이렇게나 아름답고 ♫
Have you ever seen me drunk?
내가 취하는 거 봤어?
I've never seen that.
취하는 건 못 봤지
♫And you're exceedingly adorable♫
♫ 사랑스러워 ♫
But the word "sense of propriety"
하지만 넌
is really custom-made for you.
정말 이성적이야
♫Oh, Cinderella♫
♫ 오 신데렐라여 ♫
♫My Cinderella♫
♫ 나의 신데렐라여 ♫
You were not here when I first came.
네가 오기 전인 내가 여기 온 지 1년 되던 해에
I was so hungry that
난 빈속에
I swallowed snake gall and drank goat blood.
쓸개를 삼키고 염소 피를 마셨지
I traveled through the deep forest
그리고 40kg에 달하는 짐을 얹고
with a load of 40 kilograms
깊은 숲을 드나들었어
♫Maybe you didn't♫
♫ 넌 내가 ♫
and never collapsed.
그래도 난 끄떡없었지
♫Think my heart would hurt♫
♫ 마음 아플 거란 걸 생각 못했겠지 ♫
But when I got drunk,
하지만 술만 마시면
♫If this is a dream♫
♫ 이게 꿈이라면 ♫
I thought of her.
구이샤오가 생각났어
♫I'd like to stay drunk and not wake up♫
♫ 깨어나고 싶지 않아 ♫
In a half-man tall field,
내 키의 반쯤 되는 풀숲에서
I stayed there alone,
혼자
drinking all night
술을 진탕 마시고
until I blacked out.
쓰러졌던 적이 있어
♫I used to hold back♫
♫ 참아도 봤고 ♫
♫I've waited so long♫
♫ 기다려도 봤어 ♫
♫Maybe I'm waiting for you to come♫
♫ 난 널 기다리고 있나 봐 ♫
Commissioner Du.
두 국장님
Grandpa Du.
두 할아버지
So lively.
시끌벅적하구나
I'm just passing by. Go on.
난 지나가는 길이니 다들 계속 마셔
Do what you should.
하던 거 계속해
I heard that Captain Lu
루 대장이
had prepared good wine and dishes.
한턱낸다는 소문을 듣고
My wife
우리 집사람이 글쎄
doesn't care about my dinner.
저녁을 신경 쓰지 않겠다면서
She asked me to scrounge a free meal.
나보고 여기 와서 먹으라고 하더군
So she doesn't have to cook.
저녁상을 차리지 않아도 된다면서 말이야
Sir,
두 국장님
you're wrong.
틀리셨어요
He bought the wine.
술은 루 대장이 산 거지만
But I cooked the dishes.
요리는 제가 했답니다
I see.
그렇군요
That's not right.
그건 좀 아닌데요
What's wrong?
뭐가요?
This is my restaurant.
여긴 제 가게니까
What I say is always true.
제 말대로 하셔야 해요
It's rare for them to gather here.
모처럼 모이는 건데
It's just a dinner.
밥 한 끼일 뿐이니 신경 쓰지 마세요
Have a seat.
얼른 앉으세요
I'll cook some new dishes.
요리를 더 해올게요
No need.
아니에요
Give me some peanuts
땅콩이랑
and two pieces of mutton will do.
양고기면 돼요
I'd love to do so.
제가 하겠다는 데도요
Just wait.
잠시 기다려주세요
Okay.
알았어요
Mingyu.
밍위
I heard that you are transferring your kid to another school.
샤오난을 전학 보낸다면서?
I just talked
방금 루 대장의
with Captain Lu's ex.
전 여친과 얘기 나눴어요
She is nice.
되게 좋은 분이시더라고요
She didn't mind anything
두말없이
and agreed to do it.
허락하셨어요
Ex-girlfriend?
전 여친?
During college
대학교 때 사귀던 여친 말이냐?
or later?
아니면 그 뒤에 사귄 여친이야?
During college.
대학교 때 사귀던 여자친구입니다
I've only been with her. No one else.
그 친구 말고 다른 사람은 없습니다
Can you handle it?
할 만해?
I'll help contact others if you can't.
안 되면 나도 사람 찾아볼게
I noticed that
친 대장네 일에
you really care about them.
진심이네
Of course.
당연하지
We northeasterners are grateful.
둥베이 지역 사람들은 은혜에 보답할 줄 알거든
I'm going to bed. You're leaving tomorrow.
그만 자자, 너 내일 떠나야 하잖아
♫You must have secretly collected♫
♫ 그댄 많은 어려움을 ♫
♫So much wind and frost♫
♫ 숨겼겠지 ♫
♫Waiting to meet someone♫
♫ 누군가를 만나길 기다리는 건 ♫
♫Who can know how to taste♫
♫ 자세히 음미할 수 있는 일이지 ♫
♫On a night with wine and wind♫
♫ 술도 바람도 부는 어느 밤의 ♫
♫Half a moon♫
♫ 반쪽짜리 달빛 ♫
♫The moon♫
♫ 달빛 ♫
♫You must have wiped it silently♫
♫ 그대는 분명 오랜 시간을 ♫
♫For a long time♫
♫ 묵묵히 닦아냈겠지 ♫
♫Knowing that life is silent♫
♫ 삶이 수수께끼처럼 고요할 때 ♫
♫Only have the light when it's like a mystery♫
♫ 비로소 빛이 난다는 걸 잘 알고 있어 ♫
♫On a night when no one knows♫
♫ 아무도 모르는 밤 ♫
It's windy here.
바람이 엄청 부네
♫The breeze goes everywhere♫
♫ 시원함이 가득하구나 ♫
♫The breeze♫
♫ 시원함이 ♫
♫You must have been there in secret♫
♫ 그대는 분명 가장 먼 곳을 ♫
♫To the farthest places♫
♫ 남몰래 가봤겠지 ♫
♫Bringing back the green plants of summer♫
♫ 한여름의 푸른 공기 ♫
♫And the fallen leaves of autumn♫
♫ 가을의 황금빛 들녘을 가지고 돌아왔어 ♫
♫On a night when you're dating in the garden♫
♫ 놀라서 꿈에서 깬 밤 ♫
[Home]
[집]
♫The pathos of youth is sung♫
♫ 슬픈 청춘의 노래를 부르네 ♫
Hello?
여보세요
Mom, it's me.
엄마, 나예요
You call at this hour.
왜 이렇게 늦은 밤에 전화를 했어?
Your dad will be upset.
너희 아빠가 화내실라
I have something to discuss with you.
상의할 일이 있어요
Go ahead.
말해
I can only go back to Beijing during the Chinese New Year.
연말이 돼야 베이징에 돌아갈 수 있어요
My friend's child
친구 아이가
wants to live in Beijing.
베이징에 갈 건데
I'll send him back.
집에 데려갈 테니까
Please take care of him for a few days.
며칠 좀 돌봐주세요
It's just a kid.
아이를 돌봐달라고?
You know
너희 아빠 성격을
your dad's temper.
몰라서 그래?
I think we should forget it.
그건 어려울 것 같아
Besides,
게다가
children are important
부모들은
in general families,
아이를
like their lifeblood.
목숨처럼 여겨서
Don't simply take care of others' children.
다른 집에 보내려고 하지 않아
If anything happens,
무슨 일이라도 나면
you can't pass the blame.
어떡하려고 그러니?
Your dad is awake.
너희 아빠 깨셨다
I'm hanging up.
이만 끊으마
See how smart I am.
나 똑똑하지?
I named you ZZZ
네 이름을 'ZZZ'로 저장해두면
so that you would be the last one in the phone book.
연락처 맨 끝에 있을 테니까
No one can find you.
아무도 널 찾지 못할 거야
Neither can my parents.
우리 부모님도 모르실걸
Are you still up?
아직 안 잤어?
Pack up for Qin Xiaonan.
샤오난의 짐 좀 싸줘
I'll take him back to Beijing first.
내가 데리고 베이징에 갈게
The flight is 4:20 pm
모레 오후
the day after tomorrow.
4시 20분 비행기야
I'll buy him a ticket later.
이따가 비행기 티켓 한 장 더 살게
Remember to take him to the airport
3시 전에
before 3 o'clock.
공항으로 데리고 오는 거 잊지 마
Don't miss the flight.
늦으면 안 되니까
Gui Xiao.
구이샤오
It's late at night.
늦은 밤에 샤워하면
Aren't you afraid of catching a cold after the shower?
감기 걸려
I wasn't showering.
나 샤워 안 했어
I wanted to wash my face with hot water,
뜨거운 물로 세수하려 했는데
but the water
뜨거운 물이
didn't warm up.
안 나오네
Bye.
끊을게
Pack up your son's luggage tomorrow.
내일 샤오난의 짐을 준비해놔
Gui Xiao is taking Xiaonan to Beijing
구이샤오가 모레
the day after tomorrow.
샤오난을 데리고 베이징에 가겠대
She's probably afraid that
우리가 샤오난을
it would be too late
늦게 데려갈까 봐
for us to take him there.
걱정돼서 그럴 거야
Your first love is really nice.
네 첫사랑 참 의리 있네
I've asked already.
내가 물어봤는데
She's not married yet.
구이샤오 씨 아직 미혼이래
But she helped me
그런데 구이샤오 씨가
so much with this matter.
우리를 돕는 데 열성적인 거 보니까
It seems that she still likes you.
널 아직 마음에 두고 있는 것 같아
Grab the chance.
빨리 고백해
We're not
내가 무슨
in our teens anymore.
10대 소년도 아니고
Once we're together,
고백해봤자
what can I provide her?
해줄 수 있는 게 없어